thank you very much for the introduction
and say yes I'm going to talk about
active inference which is a theoretical
framework we use to try and understand
brain function and the neurobiological
processes that underwrite a lot of the
cognitive functions that were interested
in and the the kind of central idea and
active inferences to treat everything
the brain dance as an inference problem
of some sort and that includes that
includes perceptual inference most
obviously but also for the notion of
planning as inference and and movement
itself as an inferential process
fulfilling addictions about the world
I'm going to talk about a particularly
the role of uncertainty in these kinds
of formulations because this is one of
the things that active inference does
quite well and those of you who are in
the last session of or lunch will
probably recognize a lot of the concepts
that come up here so the basic structure
is I'm going to first of all give an
overview of the idea of active inference
and just a brief summary of what it is
I'm then going to talk a bit about the
sort of neuronal networks the kinds of
architectures we might expect biological
systems to use to actually solve these
inference problems and then I'm going to
give you a couple of examples and show
some simulations that illustrate the
behavior of this kind of system first
one looking at the role of uncertainty
the idea of exploring to maximize my
information game in the environment and
the second two instead of thinking about
uncertainty about what the states and
environment causing my sensations
actually thinking about what what
influence does mine certainty about the
probabilistic structure of the world and
what influence does that have over the
Maeve as I choose to engage in so
they're thinking about the role of
learning as opposed to inference yes
okay
okay and right can you hear me now it's
that okay yeah okay I'll try and let me
know if I drop too quietly again and the
final thing I want to talk about will be
the processes that convert and the
decisions we make and the plans that
though we infer we should be following
in two movements in the real world and
I'll give you some examples for each of
those saying the key notion or the key
objective function of active inference
the key thing that everything works to
try and optimize is this free energy
functional here and this is something
that comes up in variational inference
this is just a quantity that says that
if I have some beliefs this as its
distribution Q about the states s that
are causing things in the world and then
I can I can plug them in to this
function and by minimizing now function
and I I can then get the best set of
beliefs that best describe what's going
on in the outside world that depends
upon there being some sort of
probabilistic model that I have about
about the way the world is structured
and that's given in this distribution P
so that's that's saying how how the
states s give rise to observations oh
and little the till to the line over the
top indicates that these are
trajectories we're interested in a
process that's evolving over time
they'll determine here the pie that
everything is conditioned on is the the
particular model of how things are going
to evolve all the policy that I'm going
to assume so this essentially says a
policy is just a sequence of actions or
a sequence of states that I can I can
follow
and I have several different models for
how I could behave several different
alternative policies I could engage in
and I can associate a free energy
functional with each of those that is
fine when I'm trying to make inferences
about the data I currently have the
observations that are currently
available to me it becomes much more
problematic if I then want to move into
the realm of planning because if I want
to minimize my free energy in the future
I need to try and predict what that free
energy might be and you can see here the
free energy as it is is a function of
observations of data as I don't have
data for the future yet by definition I
instead replace the expectation here or
the distribution I'm using to average
this with one that includes the
observations so I'm now predicting what
sort of observations I'm going to get
and I'm averaging this thing with
respect to both the observations and the
states that I expected to delete them
and that gives us something to think
about in terms of how we plan and how we
are we perceive these things into into
the future so once we do this we can
think of perception is the process of
optimizing this distribution q what are
my beliefs about the states of the world
at present and what will they be in the
future and and I can optimize that and I
can simply plug that in to the expected
free energy the tobo I've defined here
I'll come back to that in a second and I
can use that to to form beliefs about
the sorts of plans I'm going to engage
in the sort of policies I'll pursue so
here this is just the policy of the
belief I have about how I'm going to act
I can use that to generate an action
I'll come back to that as well and that
action changes the world generates new
observations and we get this kind of
action perception cycle with planning
and opposed then
now the reason I've put these two
equations on is just to emphasize some
important features of these two Ferengi
functionals and what they may actually
mean and here you can see that we can
react spresso thing here in terms of
this thing here which is just the
negative log probability of a certain
set of observations and you can think if
this is the evidence for the model of
all the evidence that I'm continuing to
exist I'm seeing sort of data that are
consistent with with my own model of
myself the bill is actually changing
with respect to this Q distribution is
this bit here this KL divergence this is
a non-negative quantity since it's
always positive that just quantifies how
different these two distributions are
are and here we're saying that this is
the posterior distribution the
probability of States given the data
I've already observed and and this is
our beliefs so essentially by minimizing
the free-energy
and I'm effectively reducing the distant
or I'm trying to approximate what the
true posterior should be as best as
possible using my current beliefs of
course if you were to just substitute in
the true posterior if you could
calculate that analytically then this
would just become exact inference I
point out that it depending on what
field you come from sometimes the pre
energy is represented as the negative of
what it is here particularly in machine
learning and that often leads the
rhetoric of maximizing free energy or
maximizing the evidence lower bound I'm
going to be talking about it using the
kind of physicists definition which
involves minimizing the free energy so
this is now an author pound on the
negative evidence this here is the
expected for energy rearranged in a
similar way and you see we still get
this kind of expected log evidence term
and we can think of this as being a kind
of goal directed drive this is saying
that I want to seek out though those
data that are consistent with my model
and those might be those data those
might be introspective data that
consistent with maintenance of
homeostasis or something like that they
could also be extra step to the no
goal-directed task of some sort the
interesting thing here is that the
expected KL divergence here is swapped
round just so the sign is now negative
and we now have the expected posterior
and the current posterior and the reason
for that is the way we take the
expectation here and that means that the
to minimize the expected for energy I
need to actually maximize the difference
between my beliefs as they currently
stands this Q distribution here and what
I expect my beliefs to be after making
the observations that give rise to this
posterior here so now we have an
interesting and interesting way of
thinking about what this is there's a
drive here to fulfill the kind of goal
directed predictions and there's a drive
here to try and change my beliefs as
much as possible by observing new data
so we can think of this as carving up
the expected free energy into a
component that drives exploration
information seeking behavior very much
as many of the terms did in the in the
previous talk and a drive towards
exploration and we can think we can give
these labels like intrinsic and
extrinsic value and embarrassing by
national I'll come in a moment to the
relationship between this and various
other different kinds of scheme first of
all just to make it explicit what this
looks like when when when you actually
minimize the free energy when you work
out what the posterior believes should
be so this is assuming a sort of a
partially observed Markov decision
process like a form where policies cause
state transitions and states cause
observations and so when we minimize the
free energy we essentially get my belief
about states the present is a function
of beliefs about States the past and
some transitions beliefs about the
future and some transitions and the
evidence I'm getting at the moment so
essentially we combine two empirical
priors with
with sensory evidence or evidence for
data and combine those to try and form a
posterior belief about the present and
that's our that's our perceptual
inference that minimization of the
the free energy when we when we look at
the realm of planning if we have a
private leaf that we minimize the
expected for energy the posterior belief
will contain both the expected for
energy and the free energy so here we
have another yet another expression of
the free energy and the expected for
energy and I'm just going to write out
each term in that explicitly and just
talk you through how you can intuitively
think about what this means and what is
doing the first time here we generally
refer to as accuracy so this is
essentially saying given I have several
beliefs about what sort of policies I
could engage in and I can I can take the
data I've already gathered and work out
whether that carries evidence in favor
of me pursuing one policy or pursuing
another and so here it's just saying the
observations I've observed along the
course of following this sequence of
actions is consistent with me having
followed that sequence of actions then
it's probable that I am following that
sequence of actions this term here oh
well let's go in sequence so so this
term here is the sort of thing that's
used in approaches like uncertainty
sampling looking for those data about
which I'm most uncertain so H here just
means the entropy so if I expect
something to be very very uncertain in a
particular place then it means I'm more
likely to try and try and observe those
data and learn more about the world if
we combine these two terms so here we
now have a conditional entropy that says
how reliable is the mapping from States
to observations and how informative will
they be if we combine these two terms
then we get a
and something that's been given a whole
range of different names it's sometimes
been referred to as information gain you
find this in even in the fifties
literature on base in experimental
design as the value of an experiment
based in surprise salience novelty
epistemic value and and sometimes an
intrinsic value and so this is our
information seeking component the final
bit here is just to point out that these
two things together limits how far my
beliefs about about the policy I can
pursue deviate from my prior beliefs if
they deviate a long way
then as penalized it's an excessively
complex explanation for how I could
pursue this behavior and final thing is
if this term at the end the kind of
expected evidence term and we can
interpret this in terms of an expected
utility this is the thing I'm trying to
seek out or in terms of an extrinsic
value okay so next thing to talk about
is just to think about the source of
neuronal architectures that can actually
do this sort of thing and the way we get
to that is we think we first will a
particular model in this case I'm
sticking with the Markov decision
process model and we express the free
energy in terms of the sufficient
statistics of those distributions and
the parameters of those so here we're
dealing with categorical inferences so
we're just dealing with vectors and
matrices of different kinds of
quantities so I can be in one state and
in the next day then the next stage and
there's a transition matrix that
determines how I how I go from one to
the other if we just take the free
energy gradients of that system with
respect to the beliefs about States then
we get a series of relatively simple
update equations we can do the same
thing for planning and again we can just
express these in relatively simple
linear algebra
and again these are just the free energy
gradients with respect to each of these
things and we just expressed it as a
gradient descent on the variational free
energy or in this case we set up a
belief that I'm going to minim or I'm
going to assume those policies that have
the minimal expected for energy the nice
thing about these equations is that the
dependence is between the variables
actually are quite similar to the
neuronal networks that we that we know
are present in the brain or things of a
similar form so just to give you a sense
of that we know that we we have sensory
data that's that inputs to normally
granular layer four of the cortex I know
that's three in this particular example
but we can think of those as computing a
prediction error that's the difference
between the Leafs I currently have and
the sensor in which I have and I can and
and you can see the that prediction
error also depends upon and this future
and past components here and
representing past on the Left present
future so influence from the past
inference from the future influence from
sensory data and those errors then being
used to drive that gradient descent
process I can then evaluate the expected
for energy based from that workout with
the expected for energy is and then
compute the probable policies and here's
a basic model average to work out what
are the probable states that I could be
experiencing and pursuing based upon and
based upon my beliefs about the states
under each policy and my beliefs about
the probability of perceiving each
policy okay so that's that's the sort of
architecture we would think of and this
is similar to the sort of culture code
subcortical loops that we expect to find
in the brain and this gives us a way to
start to think about how we can
interpret mirror Anatomy in terms the
inferences that it's trying to pursue
with inferences about what's actually
out there and inference is about how how
am I going to act and what will that do
to change what's out there
right so next thing I want to do is to
give you an explicit example of this in
a deliberately very simple generative
model and try and give you some
intuition for how that works so again
this is the partially observed Markov
decision process here we have our
beliefs about the policy which
influenced the transitions from state to
state we have transition matrices here
let's say well if I'm in a current state
what's the probability of being in that
state and similarly we have a mapping
here that goes from States to observable
outcomes and says what's the probability
if I'm currently in a particular stage
of observing a particular outcome and
and the key thing here is we can
actually parameterize these such that we
can alter the uncertainty in each of
these distributions and see what effect
that has the for exploratory behavior so
here in this case imagine I'm in a
particular state and each of these
represents the probability that if I'm
in that particular stage I'm going to
observe a particular outcome so here are
all the different outcomes I could
observe here we've just set up a
parameter that we've to notice our Z
term or Zeta the effectively inverse
temperature parameter on this
distribution so we can make it more or
less precise if it's very large then
this becomes almost deterministic if
it's very small then this becomes
completely flat I could observe anything
based upon where I am we've also done
the same thing for transitions here with
such parameter that essentially
quantifies how uncertain we are about
given where I am where I will be next
again if it's zero this is very flat and
then as we increase it it gets very
large and that just means that we can
control the uncertainty here what sort
of volatility of the sequence and the
uncertainty here in the mapping the
simulated agent believes
occurs between States the world and the
observations this is a you know fairly
arbitrary way of doing this we could
obviously parametrize this in lots of
different ways it's just to give you a
sense of one way in which we can do this
so this is a representation of the
generative model that I'm actually going
to show the simulation for so here I'll
go back a second so here if you imagine
what each of these each of these states
is a place I can be looking so I can
move my eyes to various different
locations and fixate different locations
in visual space and at each of those I
can see something I can get some sort of
visual or proprioceptive feedback from
where I've ended up looking and so this
just becomes the policy just becomes the
sequence of saccades the sequence of
fast eye movements I'm going to assume
in order to induce these state
transitions so here we have the hidden
states that are the fixation location so
these are all guesses so I can I can be
fixating in location one two three four
or in the center I have another set of
hidden states that I have no control
over which are which of these which of
these three squares is present in each
location so it can be either 1 2 or 3 if
I look to location 1 and the the third
the third of these squares is there then
that will map to a visual outcome that
says I'm looking at this particular
color there are transitions between
these and we can control how
deterministic or how stochastic those
transitions are and we can control the
mapping between these things so here
these are the those parameters saying
how uncertain is the mapping from stage
to observation
finally we have this this other outcome
modality this proprioceptive modality
that says where am I currently looking
and so these can transition I have
control over how these transition
together these make up the visual and
very perceptive outcomes and the
uncertainty of these transitions and the
uncertainty of this mapping can all be
manipulated and the reason for doing
that is just to show you what the
behavior of the system is when will it
be like so here we have three examples
of that same environment but with
slightly different slightly different
uncertainties in play so here we have
the simulated eye tracking trace is
interpolated between the points is just
choosing one point or the next
so it's choosing to look there there
there and exploring the environment I
should point out there's absolutely no
preferences in play here there's no
rewarding location everything here is
intrinsically motivated through the this
drive information game so you can see in
this example in every single location
the the mapping of the likelihood that
says given a stage what's the probable
observation is the same and the same is
true for the mapping from state to state
so everything is equivalently precise or
equivalently valid on here just to
illustrate what happens we've decreased
the precision of the inverse temperature
the maps States to observations so now
we have a setting we have a square here
where if I look in this location
the mapping from States to observations
is almost completely random or with it's
very small relative to relative to the
others but that essentially means that
the amount of information I can get by
looking there about the stage that's
actually there is relatively little so
here in this presence of you know
relatively noisy mapping there's not
really much point looking there because
the amount of information I can gain in
our state's the world is pretty limited
and you can actually think of this as
being a bit like a darkroom
if I look around the environment I'm not
actually going to be able to have any
sort of precise mapping in play and you
can see that it just completely ignores
that location and seeks out those where
there is a lot of information to be had
and some in psychology refer to this is
the streetlight effect which is based
upon the idea that if you're out late
one night and you've had a few drinks
and you've dropped your car keys on the
street the first place you look for them
is under the streetlight not because
it's the most likely place for them to
be but just because it's the only place
you can actually get any sort of precise
information which is incense based
optical maybe a few simulators in this
sort of setting this final example we've
decreased the precision or the inverse
temperature of the transition happening
so here things transition much more
randomly and you can see that in the
actual environment so the agent believes
it but it's also true of the environment
itself and you can see that this
location is actually fixated much more
often contrary to what's going on here
so in this particular scenario you can
think of this heuristically as I haven't
looked there in a while it's more likely
to have changed to many of the others so
there is more uncertainty to resolve
there if I haven't looked there recently
and compared to the others which will
remain relatively static or Alize
relatively predictable even in the
absence of me looking at it this
particular location is likely to change
and in an unpredictable way so I better
look back there and check okay and the
reason I put this up here is you can
interpret these parameters in terms of
which components of this drive to
explore have been altered so here we've
got the conditional engine
yes it's changed by changing this and
you can see the dots that essentially
gets larger that becomes a less probable
policy and similarly for the the change
here in the opposite direction
okay so the focus there in that
particular example was on the
uncertainty I might have about states of
the world the next thing I'm going to
talk about is the uncertainty my have in
the agile mappings between things in the
probabilistic structure of the world and
the parameters that govern that rather
than the states themselves so again we
have the same we have the same network
here but now we're going to parameterize
these mappings the a mappings that go
from States to outcomes and we're going
to say that this is something that can
be learned through the course of the
trial or across several trials and it's
this parametrized essentially using a
drill a distribution and here is an
example of the kinds of updating that
you might expect from the drill a
distribution in the scenario so again
this is if I'm in a particular stage
these are all the different observations
I could make while there if I make this
sequence of observations here but every
time I see one I update that element
essentially of that probability
distribution so more likely to see this
in future the same thing is true here
and the difference between each of these
is the choice of the initial drill a
parameters so I can actually say how
certain am I in this mapping a priori
both of them start with the belief that
the mapping is itself uniform but I can
be incredibly certain that this uniform
or I can be relatively unconfident at
its uniform and as an analogy if you
imagine you flip a coin a hundred times
and it comes up heads half the time then
you're relatively confident it's a fair
coin and a new observation is not going
to change your beliefs a great deal
whereas if I've only flipped at once or
twice before I've go ahead once and
tails once I'm going to start with the
same initial expectation of every being
fair based upon those data but a new
observation will actually cause a much
bigger change in my beliefs and that
becomes very important in the sense of
information gained about parameters
because if I'm going to behave in such a
way that I minimize my expected free
energy or maximize the difference
between my current beliefs power
parameters and my beliefs in the future
then it makes sense that I should I
should look to those regions to have a
profile more like this compared to those
like this because here I'm going to
change my beliefs a great deal more than
if I make an observation in a region
like this and I'll come back to that in
the example so the example I have here
is we have a state base that is just a
grid world so I can look at any location
in this in this world it's just me I
ain't grid and the state is where am I
currently looking in it I can then
transition between those and at each
stage I can observe one of three things
I can observe nothing I can observe a
black dot or I can observe a red dot and
the way that this is set up is that
every time I look at a particular at a
black dot it will change color so will
change from black to red this isn't
explicitly in the generative model this
is just a feature of the environment and
I can then simulate the same sort of
thing by using those same gradient
descents on the on the variational
free-energy and here you can see it's
looking around the world is it's finding
these these dots and then it's moving on
to the next one it's not looking back at
the previous one it's continuing to
explore now the motivation for this
particular task is partly due to to my
interest in thinking about how
generative models can be broken in the
sort of ways we can explain pathology in
terms of this but they also give you a
nice way of thinking about what sort of
was what sort of influences go on in
this generative model and and in
particular there's a clinical condition
called visual neglect where patients
with a stroke to the right side of their
brain normally and will often neglect
the left side of space they'll perform
viewers are cats to it so these are
attracting traces just at rest
looking at neglect patients and and a
control group you can see that they
perform many many more saccadic eye
movements to the right side of space
than
the same patients will will fail too if
you ask them two o'clock they'll draw
the right-hand side of it and not the
left and there are a range of different
phenomena that the Toccoa it is an
interesting condition that I went going
to too much detail about it now the
crucial thing is that that a common test
that's used to assess neglect is to give
people a sheet of paper with a series of
lines drawn rich and to ask them just to
cross out all of the lines and they'll
often cross out all of those on the
right rather than the left the reason
I'm talking about this is that and it's
an interesting problem thinking about
the influence is over exploratory
behavior to think what would lead a
visual search to towards counseling only
those lines on the right faces the left
or Oh or any attending to those on the
right versus the left what would lead to
this sort of scan pattern in terms of
what would have to be broken in the
generative model and so here are some
examples so here we have the same thing
I was showing you before and it looks at
both sides roughly the same number of
times and there's relatively even but
then I have three ways in which we can
break this by changing a prior belief in
the generative model to behave in an
abnormal way the first of these is very
simple we just say sorry this this
shouldn't be an expectation this is
function E and if we if we set up
privately if the time more likely to
perform secants to the right from the
left it's an almost trivial example but
it shows one way in which we can we can
produce this sort of a vis just a priori
more likely that all I'll hold up over
there the second thing we can do is
change the model such that there's a
bias and proprioceptive leads are more
likely to experience data that says I've
looked to the left oh sorry to the right
than to the left and by minimizing my
free energy either I fulfill those
predictions and I end up looking to the
right more often than to the left
but here is probably the most
interesting one this is the one I was
talking about before so we've got our
information game term where
looking at how much do my expected
beliefs diverge from my current beliefs
it's added Virgil lost and that's a good
good thing to do so in this particular
example here all we've done is we've
increased the confidence in the initial
distribution exactly as I showed you on
the previous couple of slides ago we've
set it so that your new observation will
cause a relatively small change in my
beliefs about this mapping where I
looked to what I'm going to see so the
mapping from what to wear I'm sorry even
from where to watch the where I'm
looking to which of these targets I see
becomes more confident and as if they is
modified less after a saccade to the
left versus right so if you think of the
kind of metaphor of the brain is a
scientist who is trying to work out
what's the best experiment before next
you don't do an experiment that just
changes nothing about your beliefs you
want to do the sorts of experiments that
will get your new data that will will
change your beliefs about the world and
that's exactly what we're saying here
and you can see the influence that's
having over behavior again this is just
a gradient descent on the free energy
gradients but it's giving us this
interesting pattern similar to these
other types of illusions and it's just a
speculative link between some of these
in different regions of the brain so we
can think about things like this we're
altering a mapping as altering synaptic
connections in the brain and that fits
quite nicely with ideas of long-term
plasticity synaptic modulation as a
mechanism of further learning what's
there right and so I'm going to come to
the final bit now which is thinking
about given these kinds of structures
and give it given these kinds of
architectures what we've really thought
about are how do I decide where to look
or how do I make decisions of some other
type but they're all decisions they're
all categorical I can
over there or there or there ultimately
when you actually engage with the world
you have to do it in a continuous way
you know we have to engage with
approximately Newtonian laws and
generate continuous changes in
continuous variables and so the final
that I want to talk about is is how we
actually go about doing that how we can
incorporate that into a generative model
and again appeal to exactly the same
notion of free energy minimization that
we have to to frame perception and
decision-making so this looks very
similar to what I've shown you before
but it's actually subtly different and
here I've changed the variables so these
are now continuous variables where we
have some causes in the world some
hidden states which in our X and some
sensory data but now this is not a
progression over time so the thing
that's changed here is that now we're
looking at the mapping from my position
to my velocity my velocity to my
acceleration and successive temporal
derivatives so I can now express a kind
of stochastic trajectory in terms of a
sort of Taylor series approximation
where I've just brought out all the
coefficients of that Taylor series
approximation which gives me a way of
instantaneously representing a
trajectory rather than just a current
stage for those familiar with it if you
were to truncate this here this would
essentially be an extended kalman filter
model so if we find the sorry that's all
a bit too small but and if we find the
free energy gradients for that for that
system we can reconstruct a similar
network if it relies upon errors here
the drive changes in expectations and
and and then those influence the
higher-level causes and what's going on
my
my errors about the states themselves so
this can be extended hierarchically
essentially indefinitely so some of you
may recognize this as being a predictive
coding architecture well where we are
just passing prediction errors and
expectations around again this is the
position velocity acceleration the new
aspect of this that wasn't in what I
showed you previously is this fit here
you probably can't read that very
clearly but that essentially says the
action now is also going to follow a
gradient descent on the free energy the
only thing action can change from the
perspective the generation model here is
the it's the data itself so I can either
optimize my beliefs about the date or I
can change the data source it becomes
more consistent with my model and when
we frame it like that
we see that with the free energy
gradients take the form of essential
weighted prediction error and so I can
treat action as being I get some sensory
data i compute an error that drives an
action which then in this particular
case moves my eyes such that it fulfills
any prediction error that's in play and
so we get watch neuroscientists have
studied for centuries now the idea of a
classical reflex arc okay yeah so what
if described here gives you a way of if
you have some private leaves about what
sort of trajectories you're going to
engage in then you can you can then
implement those trajectories but the big
question is where where do those prior
believes actually come from OS shape so
here's an example of some a simulation
using these equations that the treats
the eyes both as spheres the agent can
and can change the acceleration or the
circular acceleration of the eyes and
they obey essentially Newton's second
law for rotational systems by adding in
a prior belief about the sorts of
chariot engages in you can see that the
eyes then follow that trajectory and
giving a different prior beliefs gives
you all sorts of different all different
sorts of ocular motor behaviors in this
particular example we've used the same
sort of thing to simulate things like
handwriting and various other types of
behavior with exactly the same set of
equations but different generative
models in the past and yes so the next
question was was where do these
primaries come from so I have this
network if I'm if I if I set some prior
belief about V then this will cause a
particular change in trajectory which
will cause particular data that I will
predictions about data to tell then
fulfill by acting and but I can push the
network that I described above on top of
this one so I can I can just say that
instead of this being an observation in
and of itself this is actually just
another random variable the index is
which of these continuous variables to
make use of so you can think of this as
a process of forming different
hypotheses that then have to be
implemented in the continuous domain
different alternative alternative
trajectories that I could choose from
and I infer which one is most probable
based upon believes here which includes
all of the exploratory and and and
pragmatic behavior but then I can map
that down into this continuous model
with several different hypotheses and
then pass messages back up that are
effectively the evidence for each of
those models so I have a hypothesis that
I might look over there this is a
hypothesis son I look over there each of
those can be mapped to a prior belief
that my eyes will end up in this
continuous location or this continuous
location
and and then I can I can allow those
continuous dynamics play out evaluate
the evidence for each of those and pass
that back up to say what was the more
probable location that I my eyes went to
so he get a process of decisions going
down to movements and messages being
passed back up again and you start to
get this hierarchical structure where
you can pass messages both up and down
again you can extend each of these
indefinitely hierarchically so you can
repeat this above itself and above
itself and similarly you can have many
many layers of this and get fairly
complicated and models overall so this
is just a summary of what I've said over
the previous few slides this idea that
we can have these discrete equations
that are playing out that has said these
discrete inferences that are playing out
that is saying what are the most
probable policies I'm going to pursue
what are the most probable States the
result from that and what are the most
probable outcomes and observations that
I'll get based upon that these feed down
through essentially model averaging a
bit like a mixture of gaussians from a
discrete variable a categorical variable
to a continuous variable we then perform
these filtering steps that essentially
behave a bit like an extended Kalman
filter but with action added on and then
we pass that all up again evaluate the
evidence for each different alternative
model which we can do fairly efficiently
using Bayes and mul reduction and pass
that up to inform the next step so we
can get this kind of complete perception
action cycle so we can see how that
might be implemented in the anatomy of
the brain and we've argued some of these
structures more than others that pretty
good evidence that things like the basal
ganglia might evaluate the evidence of
different kinds of policies behavioral
Tetris I could engage in on the left
we're just showing these some of the
inferences that happen a teacher status
so this is which the the states under
each different kind of policy which
location am I going to look at and I'm
inferring those both of the present time
and a future time steps I then map that
through with this bit so this is
representing the kind of topography of
the superior colliculus in the midbrain
and the idea here is that each location
in the colliculus represents a different
hypothesis about where I could look and
this red dot indicates the error between
where I'm currently looking and where I
think I should be looking and you can
see that as we form an inference about
the next stage its moves out and as the
error increases I now believe I should
be looking somewhere else as the eyes
move there that error closes in there is
a cell population in the superior
colliculus the behaves almost exactly
like this and so it seems again very
biologically plausible okay and so that
is the end of what I want to say I just
wanted to thank these various people and
my funders in university and thank you
for listening so anyone have any
questions
[Music]
[Applause]